<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cherry on Arvola Woodwork</title><link>/tags/cherry/</link><description>Recent content in cherry on Arvola Woodwork</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/cherry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cat Shrine</title><link>/post/old/shrine/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/old/shrine/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project I originally completed in 2019.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="ashrine.jpg"
alt="Figure 1. Finished cat shrine."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 1. Finished cat shrine.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I designed a shrine to hold the ashes
and paw prints of our passed cats, with room for decorations and, of course,
live cats as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Several pieces of a pile of local cherry I bought had some highly figured
crotch at the ends of the boards. The design highlights the unusual figure
of those boards as a wide open shelf. I even left some of the bark on, and
just strengthened it with shellac.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="bottom.jpg"
alt="Figure 2. Figure on the bottom shelf."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 2. Figure on the bottom shelf.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>At the left, I attached a side board using dovetails to the bottom shelf,
and then using a rabbet in the side board attached a back panel for the
smaller shelves. The back is also attached to the bottom using a dowel,
but that&amp;rsquo;s only near the left edge to allow for wood movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="photo-gallery ">
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="2-gallery-0"
checked="checked"
name="gallery2"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="back.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 3. Gluing the back piece on.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="2-gallery-0"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(back.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="2-gallery-1"
name="gallery2"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="oops.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 4. The figured wood is brittle in places. I fixed it with glue.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="2-gallery-1"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(oops.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The shelves were glued in mostly to the left board as well, rather than the
back. I wanted to make sure the movement of the back panel would not cause
issues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added little pegs to the perimiter of the small shelves to make sure cats
couldn&amp;rsquo;t knock the boxes out of the shelves. The pegs I made from a long dowel
of walnut&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="shelf.jpg"
alt="Figure 5. Walnut pegs on the shelf."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 5. Walnut pegs on the shelf.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Lastly, I added another wider shelf at the top using another end piece,
as a place for cats to sit. This final shelf is attached with a mortise
and tenon through the shelf.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="cat.jpg"
alt="Figure 6. Making use of the top shelf."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 6. Making use of the top shelf.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Thank you for reading.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Library Cart</title><link>/post/old/librarycart/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/old/librarycart/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project originally done in 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is the first real piece of furniture I made, a full-size library cart
as a gift for my wife.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="cart.jpg"
alt="Figure 1. The finished cart."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 1. The finished cart.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I had recently bought a large amount of cherry. The Woodshop had a big stack
of large cherry pieces from a locally cut down tree, and I bought everything
they had left. I believe it was around 120 board feet. It had lots of
beautiful figure, but without a lot of cracking, so ideal for fine furniture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="raw-ends.jpg"
alt="Figure 2. Both end pieces from a single board."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 2. Both end pieces from a single board.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I had a good idea of what I wanted the cart to be like, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t look for
existing designs. I wanted it to be sturdy and solid, even if it was
overloaded with books. I did some rough calculations, and it should be
able to handle at least 400 kg of load (900 lb).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="live-edge.jpg"
alt="Figure 3. Live edge before (bottom) and after cleanup."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 3. Live edge before (bottom) and after cleanup.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The pieces for the ends had a nice live edge, so I wanted to preserve it.
I cleaned up the bark with a pullshave, and then cleaned up the top layer
with a spokeshave and a gouge. I cut the opposite side so that the live
edge could be at the front of the cart, and the back a straight cut line
that narrows the cart slightly towards the top.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the top of the ends, I rounded it off with a gentle curve, and then
cut a long opening following the curve to create a nice handle for pulling
the cart.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="handle.jpg"
alt="Figure 4. Curved handle at the top."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 4. Curved handle at the top.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Laying out the joinery in the end pieces was a bit more challenging due to
the unusual shape and angle. I butted up the two pieces so that the inside
was facing up, clamped them down to prevent movement, and laid everything
out symmetrically from the middle.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="layout.jpg"
alt="Figure 5. Laying out the joinery."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 5. Laying out the joinery.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It was slow going, and I was afraid of having issues with the markings not
matching up, but fortunately everything lined up beautifully.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to use through tenons for the bottom rails and the top shelf,
and stopped tenons for the rest of the shelves. That way I could be sure
the overall structure held with the addition of wedges to the tenons, but
not adding unnecessary holes to the beautiful wood panels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The large bottom shelf is angled back a little to keep books from sliding
forward as the cart is moved. It also makes it easier to see the spines of
the books. I made sure to leave a small gap at the back between the shelf
and the back board so dust and dirt wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get trapped there.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="ends.jpg"
alt="Figure 6. Ends laid out and cut."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 6. Ends laid out and cut.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I wanted to make sure the bottom of the cart could hold heavy casters,
so instead of using a shelf, I made two heavy rails. The rails are 2&amp;quot;
thick and about 4½&amp;quot; wide.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="rails.jpg"
alt="Figure 7. Rails cut from a thicker piece."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 7. Rails cut from a thicker piece.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I added a lip to the short middle shelf, so when you push something to the
shelf, there&amp;rsquo;s no chance of it falling out the back. I also added a lip to
the bottom of the top shelf for added rigidity, although I expect that wasn&amp;rsquo;t
really necessary. The top shelf has no lip on top of it, so it&amp;rsquo;s clear for
setting large things on it, or for using it as a table for a laptop.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="lip.jpg"
alt="Figure 8. Gluing a lip to the short shelf."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 8. Gluing a lip to the short shelf.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Thanks to the heavy rails on the bottom, I could use large brass inserts for
holding bolts for the casters. I liked the idea of using the inserts to make
it possible to remove or change the casters without any concern for wearing
out a screw hole in wood.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="photo-gallery ">
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="8-gallery-0"
checked="checked"
name="gallery8"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="caster-insert.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 9. Brass insert for bolts.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="8-gallery-0"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(caster-insert.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="8-gallery-1"
name="gallery8"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="caster.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 10. Heavy duty caster.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="8-gallery-1"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(caster.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="8-gallery-2"
name="gallery8"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="parts.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 11. All the parts before assembly.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="8-gallery-2"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(parts.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="gallery-item">
&lt;input
type="radio"
id="8-gallery-3"
name="gallery8"
class="gallery-selector"
/>
&lt;div class="gallery-img">
&lt;img src="glue.jpg" alt="" />
&lt;div class="gallery-caption">Figure 12. Gluing up the whole thing at once.&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;label
for="8-gallery-3"
class="gallery-thumb"
style="background-image: url(glue.jpg);"
>&lt;/label>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Lastly, the cart was finished using blonde shellac. After 4 coats, I sanded
the surface to 600 grit, and rubbed it first with steel wool, and then with
pumice and mineral spirits to give it a smooth, dull glow.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="cart2.jpg"
alt="Figure 13. Showing the smooth finish."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 13. Showing the smooth finish.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Thank you for reading.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>