<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Arvola Woodwork</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Arvola Woodwork</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Foot Stool</title><link>/post/old/stool/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/old/stool/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project I originally completed in 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="00-stool.jpg"
alt="Figure 1. Finished foot stool."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 1. Finished foot stool.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>After I finished the workbench, I made my first major purchase for
woodworking in the form of a stack of 10 foot long cherry lumber,
and a few pieces of walnut.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The walnut was 6/4 (ie. 1.5 inches, or 35 mm), a perfect thickness for
creating a solid foot stool. It was a pretty straight-forward project to attempt,
and I wanted to keep it simple for my first furniture project. This one is
also a &lt;a href="https://woodworkingmasterclasses.com/videos/foot-stool-project-info/" target="_blank">Paul Sellers project&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="parts.jpg"
alt="Figure 2. Parts cut and shaped."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 2. Parts cut and shaped.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The legs were all shaped by hand using a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spokeshave" target="_blank">spokeshave&lt;/a>. I found an
old Stanley 151 for sale at &lt;a href="https://hyperkitten.com/" target="_blank">Hyperkitten Tool Company&lt;/a>,
probably made in the 1910s. Using a spokeshave is very pleasing; it is
a very minimal tool. It&amp;rsquo;s very light and moves without much pressure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The holes in the base were made with a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brace_%28tool%29" target="_blank">brace and bit&lt;/a>, and it was
the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve used one. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t as challenging to use as I
expected; with the 1&amp;quot; (26 mm) drill bit, it didn&amp;rsquo;t take very long.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="brace.jpg"
alt="Figure 3. My Miller&amp;amp;rsquo;s Falls brace and a few bits."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 3. My Miller&amp;rsquo;s Falls brace and a few bits.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="gluing.jpg"
alt="Figure 4. Gluing the parts together."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 4. Gluing the parts together.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The legs go through the base, with glue on the mating surface. Wedges
are then tapped in with some more glue to create a mechanical joint
in addition to the glue. It&amp;rsquo;s a very strong joint.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The protruding parts of the legs were then trimmed and the bottoms
leveled by scribing them on a flat surface. Finally, the stool was
finished with shellac.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are quite a few small imperfections on the stool: the legs
don&amp;rsquo;t splay evenly, the tops of the legs have indentations from
scribing a sizing guide, and some tearing is visible in the wood.
They are fairly minor though, and certainly don&amp;rsquo;t detract from its
function.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I made a similar stool about a year and a half later, and it was
clear how much my skills had improved. The second stool was sized
to fit a cat bed so our cats could sit up above the table and
watch us play board games.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="twostools.jpg"
alt="Figure 5. The first stool on the left and new on the right."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 5. The first stool on the left and new on the right.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="lumi.jpg"
alt="Figure 6. Newer stool in use."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 6. Newer stool in use.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Thank you for reading.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Workbench</title><link>/post/old/workbench/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/old/workbench/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project I originally completed in 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a long time I wanted to get into woodworking. I had some experience through
school, as I always selected woodworking for elective classes. The projects at
school were always relatively simple and largely relied on machines, so that
remained in my mind as the definition of woodworking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Based on those experiences, I occasionally researched the various machines I
would need to get for starting out. Generally speaking they&amp;rsquo;re either poorly
made or very expensive, and require a lot of room. That made me hold off on
getting started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then one day, by chance, I stumbled upon a series of videos by
&lt;a href="https://paulsellers.com/" target="_blank">Paul Sellers&lt;/a> where he builds a workbench.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ru2ZiNs_Wek" target="_blank">&lt;img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/ru2ZiNs_Wek/hq720.jpg"
alt="Figure 1. How to build a workbench by Paul Sellers"/>&lt;/a>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 1. How to build a workbench by Paul Sellers&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>What really captivated me was the minimal amount of tools used and the
lack of a workshop. There were no machines, no existing workbench, not
even a roof over his head. With a few hand tools and using cheap hardware
store lumber, he built a solid workbench.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It felt immediately accessible. &amp;ldquo;I could do this,&amp;rdquo; I thought, with minimal
investment. I rented a pickup truck and bought about $150 worth of 2x4 lumber
from a hardware store. I bought a few cheap chisels, a #4 plane by Woodriver,
two hand saws and some clamps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, I built two simple sawhorses, and I set an old hollow core door on top.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="workbench_1.jpg"
alt="Figure 2. Gluing the first of the two top slabs."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 2. Gluing the first of the two top slabs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I followed Paul Seller&amp;rsquo;s instructions more or less exactly, so I won&amp;rsquo;t go
into too much detail on the build itself. One difference was that the wood
I got had much more rounded corners and wasn&amp;rsquo;t as even, so it took more work
to flatten the slabs. To make that easier I bought a second plane, a
&lt;a href="https://www.leevalley.com/en-us/shop/tools/hand-tools/planes/scrub/51871-veritas-scrub-plane" target="_blank">Veritas scrub plane&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="scrub.jpg"
alt="Figure 3. Speeding up flattening with a scrub plane."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 3. Speeding up flattening with a scrub plane.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="legs.jpg"
alt="Figure 4. Legs assembled with mortise and tenon joints."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 4. Legs assembled with mortise and tenon joints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="hand-tools">Hand tools&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At this point I had watched and read more material by &lt;a href="https://paulsellers.com" target="_blank">Paul Sellers&lt;/a>
about using hand tools for woodworking, and I was finding that I enjoyed
the work immensely - more so than in the past with machines.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All your senses
tell you about the wood you&amp;rsquo;re working with, rather than the machines. You feel
changes in the growth of the wood rather than vibrations of the tool. You hear
the texture of what you&amp;rsquo;re working with rather than the deafening cacophony of
motors and high-speed blades. You breathe and smell the wood rather than wear
a dust mask constantly. To me it feels more like crafting with skill rather than just
building.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To be clear, I don&amp;rsquo;t say that to seem somehow superior, it&amp;rsquo;s mostly just my
preference. Power tools and machines have their advantages as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall hand tools take more time and effort, but I&amp;rsquo;m not in any hurry - it is a
hobby after all. Hand tools are also more of a learning experience, it takes a lot of
practice to use them effectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I do still occasionally use power tools. I have a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brace_%28tool%29" target="_blank">brace&lt;/a> that I typically
use for larger holes, but for smaller ones I use a power drill. When I occasionally
need plywood panels, I usually cut those with a circular saw.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="finishing-the-workbench">Finishing the workbench&lt;/h2>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="jaw.jpg"
alt="Figure 5. Shaping the vise jaw."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 5. Shaping the vise jaw.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The only major change from the original was that I used a different vise. I got
a &lt;a href="https://www.leevalley.com/en-us/shop/tools/workshop/workbenches/vises/67755-veritas-quick-release-front-vise?item=05G3401" target="_blank">vise mechanism by Veritas&lt;/a>
and made a heavy cherry jaw for it.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="complete.jpg"
alt="Figure 6. Completed workbench."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Figure 6. Completed workbench.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Thank you for reading the first post on my woodworking blog. I intend to write
up a record of my past projects, and this was the first one.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About</title><link>/about/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>This will be a simple site logging my woodworking experiences.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will try to update it as my projects move forward, and I intend
to slowly add posts for older projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few technical details:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is written in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown" target="_blank">Markdown&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank">Hugo&lt;/a> is responsible for turning the content into
a website. I considered others as well, but Hugo seems to have the best
support.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The site is hosted on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/InterPlanetary_File_System" target="_blank">IPFS&lt;/a>,
with the help of &lt;a href="https://www.pinata.cloud/" target="_blank">Pinata&lt;/a>.
&lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/" target="_blank">Cloudflare&lt;/a> makes the website accessible through a normal
browser, instead of needing to support IPFS.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The theme is based on &lt;a href="https://github.com/queensferryme/hugo-theme-texify/" target="_blank">hugo-theme-texify&lt;/a>,
I enjoy the academic look of LaTeX.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title/><link>/archives/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/archives/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>